[Music]
good evening good day everybody
great to be back welcome to episode
eight
of hashtag ask abhijit today is the
astrophysics special
so today is going to be a 60 minute
episode we're going to keep it
fast and snappy and i am so happy that
i've got so many questions from you
very interesting and intelligent
questions
uh it would i think it will take me 10
episodes to cover them all
all and i can sense that these are the
some of the questions that you were not
allowed to ask
in school etc so i will answer your
questions
so let's get right into it with question
number one which is
by akshat tundia
akshat asks is if the observable
universe is 60 billion light years wide
or in diameter so how come it is just
13.8 billion
years old that's a very good very
intelligent question
so the universe as we know from our best
understanding
is 13.8 billion years old approximately
so if light travels for 13.8 billion
years
then the edge of the universe from where
we are
should be 13.8 billion light years away
so the radius of the universe should be
13.8 billion years
and the diameter should be approximately
billion years uh 28 billion light years
or so
however what we find is that the
diameter is about 90
billion light years so the radius is
about 46
or so billion light years the radius of
the observable universe
so what explains this incredible
discrepancy
and the explanation is that the
expansion of the universe
is accelerating and the space
time that the fabric fabric of the
universe space time
it can expand at speeds that are greater
than the speed of light
and that does not violate the laws of
physics
so that is the thing so we know that
there is this
cosmic universal speed limit in our
universe
the speed of light which is about 300
kilometers per second that is a speed of
light
and that is the fastest that anything
can travel
inside the universe inside space-time
inside the fabric
of space-time and it's only massless
particles such as the photon
that can travel at this speed massive
particles
can never reach that speed because of
the laws of relativity
if you study special relativity it
becomes very simple very obvious why
massive particles cannot attain the
speed of light because to attain that
speed they would have need to have
their mass would increase to infinity
essentially
so massive particles can't travel that
fast so we have this universal speed
limit
and yes and yet the fabric of space-time
itself
has no such speed limit it can expand at
any speed
so for example when the universe was
just a millisecond
old just a millisecond after the big
bang
the cosmic horizon was about a light
year wide
it was about the horizon that you could
see the how far you could see was about
a light year away
so it ex the universe the fabric of
space time expanded
super luminally so right after the so
the the big bang
there is there was this period called
cosmic inflation in which the universe
expanded
to an enormous degree and this was a
super luminal expansion it expanded
thousands of times
the speed of light so while we cannot
travel
within the fabric of space time which is
the stage upon which everything happens
while we cannot travel within space time
at the speed of light
if we are massive objects nevertheless
the fabric of space-time itself can
expand at any rate
and as we know as as i hope you know
the universe is expanding and the
expansion
of the universe is accelerating so it's
expanding faster and faster
at the largest scales of of of the
universe
so at the local scale where we are in
this room where i'm sitting i don't see
i don't observe any expansion of space
time because
i because of and why that is so i will
get into that
in in a few minutes so this expansion
happens only at the
very largest scales at the scales of
galaxy super clusters and larger than
that
so because the universe has been
expanding in the in the universe
the x expansion is accelerating and it
can
actually expand faster than the speed of
light that's why
what we observe is that despite the
universe being only 13.8 billion years
old
the cosmic horizon the obs the horizon
of the observable universe
has a radius of about 46 billion light
years or a diameter of roughly
90 billion light years so that's a very
intelligent
question a very incisive question and
these are the kind of questions
that lead us to understand physics and
science and nature
better so great question and let's get
on with the next question
so this is by jay saxena
how vast is our universe how can
astrophysicists assume
that we have discovered this amount of
space only
if we do not know how vast is our
universe
so we have the cosmic horizon which is
the
observable universe which is the
furthest
we can look with uh any instrument that
we have
and that's about 46 billion light years
away so
let me share an image with you
so this here is an is an approximate
representation
of this so the size the present size of
the observable universe is about 46
billion light years we know this because
that's
how far we can see we can calculate the
distance using uh techniques such as red
shift
in which light is it gets its
wavelength gets stretched out as it
travels because of the expansion of
space time
so we can calculate how far away a
certain object is based on the redshift
that we see in the in the light spectra
from that object for example a distant
galaxy so we know that the
cosmic horizon the observable horizon
the size of the observable universe is
about
46 billion light years in diameter it's
a sphere
of of radius 46 billion light years the
amount of this of this observable
universe that we can actually reach
at the speed of light is about 13.8
light years
or if you just consider the expansion of
space-time etc
it would be about 14.5 billion light
years so that's how far we can send
light further than that we cannot even
send light
because the universe is expanding
further than that it speeds faster than
light itself now how how
large is the actual universe well we
don't have
any clue at all the actual universe
which lies beyond
the cosmic horizon could be enormous
and we can only speculate and even those
speculations will
be based less because we have no
observational evidence or data
or any sort of uh fundamental
understanding of what would be a
tentative or rough
size of the universe that lies beyond
the cosmic horizon so we don't know it
could even be infinite who knows we
don't know right now
so we are limited by our observations by
our limitations
to observing us a slice
a certain portion of the actual universe
and that
is a sphere of radius 46 billion light
years
so we we don't assume that we have
discovered a certain amount of space
we can calculate it using techniques
such as
redshift so we know how far is the
furthest
uh object that we have ever
seen which is a very distant in a very
faint galaxy
and also there's another technique there
is something called cosmic microwave
background radiation
which is something i'll go into later
that also gives us a certain
kind of uh certain kind of handle on how
old the universe is and certain
parameters of the universe
so we have these different disparate
clues
and we use these clues to put together a
rudimentary
uh tentative understanding of the
universe and
and what we have achieved in the past
century or so has been significant
progress
we understand the universe reasonably
well we have
we have good reasonably good theory of
how the universe
formed the so-called big bang theory we
have the standard model of particle
physics
we have the theory of general relativity
and we have quantum mechanics so all of
these put together give us a good
idea of how the universe actually is but
there is a lot to discover as we shall
see
in subsequent questions so this is a
good question
great
so this is by anish curry what's the
difference between dark matter and
anti-matter or is it the same thing
well dark matter and antimatter are not
the same thing
and so what is dark matter dark matter
is a missing uh it is a missing it is an
it is an unidentified component of the
mass
energy composition of the universe so
let me
show you let me share a screen with you
okay let's take a look at this so this
is the matter energy mass energy
composition of the universe
about 4.9 percent of the universe
is ordinary matter so this is everything
you can see in the universe
all the planets and stars and
nebulae and galaxies and all other
luminous matter
this is just four point nine percent of
the actual universe
so we understand less than five percent
of the actual universe right more than
of the universe is entirely unknown to
us
we do not have the even the basic
understanding of what it is
we know the composition so about 26.8
percent or thereabouts is
what we call dark matter and the
remaining portion about 68
is what is called dark energy now dark
energy is a really mysterious thing
dark matter is slightly better
understood it is
something that is uh that interacts only
gravitationally
it does not interact by the
electromagnetic interaction or the weak
interaction or the strong interaction
it only interacts with ordinary matter
via the force
of gravity so this could be some for
form of
uh purely gravitating particle or it
could be a class
a family of particles we seriously don't
know at this point
we have a number of theories but as of
now there is absolutely
no direction there are many theories
some are
some are more more uh so some theories
are more
in vogue right now some theories are
less in vogue but
none of these theories has ever come
close
to being proven or or in any way at all
so that is what dark matter is and how
did we discover dark matter is an
interesting story so when we
look at uh galaxies we can calculate the
amount of mass
in a galaxy based on
we can calculate the amount of mass in a
galaxy based on the
the light output of the galaxy so we can
estimate the number of stars and the
mass
that is in a galaxy and then we can and
we know that galaxies they rotate around
their
their axis or around their center so
based on the laws of physics and the
amount of mass a galaxy contains
based on the light it emits we can
uh tentatively uh estimate
or predict how fast its arms will be
rotating
how far how fast they will be going
around the center of the galaxy
and the predictions never match
observations
the predictions are in lie are supposed
to be in line with kepler's second law
in case you have studied that but what
we find is that
it doesn't work that way the galaxy's
arms move at a
very different rate so let me show that
it's called
rotation curves and this is what it is
so this white dashed line over here
if you can see my pointer the white
dashed line is what we expect from the
visible disk of
of a typical galaxy this is based on
estimations on calculations based on the
laws of physics and based on the
amount of uh matter we can observe
and what we see is very different the
yellow and blue
points are observational evidence and
they are very very different
so the rotation curves of galaxies are
very different they rotate
faster than what we would expect them to
and
and the the best way to explain
this discrepancy is to hypothesize that
the galaxies contain
some invisible matter which is which far
exceeds the visible matter
so this is what we call a dark matter
hello and
this explains the discrepancy in the
rotation curves
of of galaxies so this is how the idea
of dark matter first
emerged and then now we have seen other
evidence of dark matter for example
gravitational lensing etc
so that in brief is dark matter what is
anti-matter
antimatter is essentially anti-particles
see
ordinary matter like us right or our
bodies etc everything we know
is composed of uh subatomic particles
protons neutrons electrons and so forth
right that is our ordinary baryonic
matter and hydronic matter
now antimatter is composed of
anti-protons anti-neutrons
anti-electrons
so an anti-particle is has the same
exact same mass as a regular particle
but it's
charged its charge is flipped it's
opposite so an anti-proton
has a negative charge and the same
mass as the regular proton which has a
positive charge
an anti-electron or a positron has a
positive charge and the same mass
as a regular electron and anti-neutrons
also exist which have uh
which have anti-quarks instead of the
regular quarks which
make up a neutron so anti-matter happens
it it manifests itself at the baryonic
level and even at the quark level so
so that's what anti-matter is it's
essentially uh
it has opposite charges and certain
quantum numbers are also
different but the masses are the same
so an anti-proton and a positron could
get together
and combine to form an atom of
anti-hydrogen
so that's what anti-matter antimatter or
antimatter is
the the thing about antimatter is that
it immediately annihilates
when it comes into contact with regular
matter so if a proton
would come into contact with an entire
proton they would immediately annihilate
annihilate each other and give off
photons
so these two masses they will combine
and produce pure energy in the form of
of in the form of photons by the very
famous equation which we all know e
equals mt squared
so it is very difficult to uh so
antimatter has been observed
it it is produced regularly in large
colliders such as the large hadron
collider and other such
instruments it's also emitted in in
certain
forms of radiation for example you have
positrons that are emitted
from certain kinds of radiation which
has given rise to this technology called
positron
emission tomography pet you know about
the pet scans pet scans
so that is a technology which has been
developed
because of the emission of positrons
which is anti-matter
from radiation and so there are various
ways of producing
antimatter but it is very difficult to
store it because like i said
the moment it comes into contact with
regular matter it
it just explodes it gives off a large
amount of energy
so to store antimatter you would have to
keep
you would have to confine it in a pure
vacuum
you could you cannot even have a single
molecule of oxygen or nitrogen or
anything in there
and it has to be confined in the center
of
of a container which is mac which has
vacuum so you would need some form of
magnetic field to confine it there
so it's very difficult to produce any
quantity any significant quantity of
antimatter
and it's even more difficult to store it
so that is what
anti-matter is dark matter and
antimatter are very different things
and dark parity is something which is
even more different
so i hope that answers your question
anish
next question
this is by bhabho pradhan if our
universe
expansion accelerates so how does our
universe get
an external force to accelerate this is
a brilliant question if i would have
asked this question in school or college
they would have told me that i'm stupid
this is a stupid question but it's not a
stupid question
it is questions such as these that
that basically make us explore the
concepts
and clarify the concepts properly so if
you ask this question and you get the
answer then you will understand the
concept better
so this is a great question and it's a
very valid question the universe is
excellent it's expand
the universe is expanding first of all
and secondly
this expansion is accelerating it's
getting faster
so what is the force that is causing
this is it is there something outside
the
universe that is that is uh
imparting some sort of energy or force
into this universe
is that what's driving this expansion or
is there some other mechanism
brilliant question so the answer lies
in what we call dark energy
so let me go back to this
let me share that image once again here
we are
so like i mentioned uh like this pie
chart tells you about about 68
almost 70 percent of the mass energy
content
of the universe is dark energy
so we don't know what this is we know
that it
it functions as a kind of repulsive
gravity
as if it's a it's an anti-gravity kind
of force it it pushes
objects apart it pushes things apart but
only at the very largest
scales so the the
density of dark energy in the universe
is is very very very less
it's less than 10 to the minus 30 10 to
the minus 30 grams
per cubic centimeter so you can see it's
very very dilute and that's why in this
room nothing is moving apart
because it is so incredibly dilute and
yet
in the universe space interstellar space
is mostly empty space
most of it is just empty and it is this
enormous
this enormity of emptiness and the this
dilute
dark energy which is inside it so all of
this dark
energy in this empty space it adds up
and it adds up to
almost 70 percent of the mass energy of
the of the universe
so because it is so dilute it doesn't
have any effect at small scales like in
the room
that i am in or in our solar system or
even even our galaxy
or even in our local galaxy cluster but
it does push objects apart like super
clusters of galaxy et cetera
at the very largest cosmic scales at the
very largest astrophysical scales
so that is what dark energy is it is
some kind of force it may be
a new new force of of nature
or it could be some substance some kind
of fluid some
we don't know what it is but we know it
is there and we know it's
it's accelerating the expansion of the
universe it's essentially creating new
space
a new new space time everywhere so new
space time
is somehow emerging out of the amount of
space time that we
currently have and that is causing the
universe to expand faster and faster and
faster away
so that is what dark energy is it is the
it is one of the biggest
mysteries that we have in astrophysics
today
it is one of the biggest unsolved
problems in astrophysics and
we don't even know where to begin right
now we don't have we have some
some theories some hypotheses etc but
there is at present no way to confirm
or or refute these theories and
hypotheses so
so to answer your question once again
our universe expands
and its expansion is accelerating
because of something
within the universe itself this
so-called dark energy
which is either a fluid or a repulsive
form of gravity or some sort of force
which is causing the universe to expand
there's nothing coming from outside the
universe
as far as we know but we don't know
because we don't know what's outside the
universe we cannot look outside the
universe
because like i said earlier we can only
observe a small portion of the universe
we don't know what's beyond that
and we can't even reach that that cosmic
horizon because
we don't have the means to do that so we
don't know what's outside the universe
do we have a multiverse do we have an
entire universe
of some kind we don't know so
so maybe your question is valid maybe
there could be something
from outside the universe that somehow
imbuing our universe and its space time
with some force or energy
that is well i think that's a valid
hypothesis
it is a valid hypothesis because it
can't be proved right now but
yeah there could be some such mechanism
but the to
the to the best of our understanding and
and the theory that's most widely
accepted
is this uh theory of dark energy which
is
some kind of force or some kind of
substance or some fluid that
acts as if it is a repulsive form of
gravity
and it actually creates more space time
as it goes along
so i hope that answers your question
that's a great question
[Music]
this is by akash puller hello akash good
to see you again
could you please explain what is cosmic
microwave background radiation
good question cmbr
so the cosmic okay so let's say i have a
telescope
okay i take the telescope i look out
into the
interstellar space and i see darkness
and i see some stars and some galaxies
but it's mostly black it's mostly dark
right
now you can take the most powerful
telescope that you have the most
powerful
optical telescope that you have and you
will again see
you will be able to see many more stars
and galaxies you will be able to see
much further away
but you will see this darkness and yet
when you have a
very powerful and sensitive radio
telescope for example
then you detect that a certain kind of
noise in the background it's as if there
is a certain
glow a very very weak glow that is that
permeates the entire
universe but it's not visible to the
naked eye and the wavelength
of this glow the wavelength of this
radiation it is electromagnetic
radiation
its wavelength is about from a
millimeter to a meter long
and it's extremely cold it's about 2.7
or so degrees above degrees kelvin above
absolute zero
so it's almost at almost at absolute
zero just a little
fraction just a little notch above the
absolute coldest temperature that you
can have in the universe
but it is still there and this radiation
this ancient
glow permeates the entire known universe
and what this is is it is the oldest
electromagnetic radiation that was that
was ever
uh formed in the universe it dates back
to about
370 000 years after the big bang
during the epoch of recombination when
the
when when protons and electrons
first combined to form stable atoms
to form stable hydrogen atoms so this is
the epoch of
recombination and that's when this
radiation first was was first
formed and this radiation persists to
to this day it was much hotter earlier
during that
epoch of riemann normal recombination
today it has
become very very cold and its wavelength
has shifted it's become very
much longer so it's in the microwave
wavelength
and it is the oldest radiation that we
know it is almost
like the after glow of the big bang
itself
almost like that so it tells us a lot
about the early about the early universe
it is one of the major proofs that we
have of the big
bang theory the big bang model of
cosmology
so there are two things that essentially
have helped us understand
that something called the big bang
actually happened the first thing
is that there is this accelerating
expansion of the universe the cosmic red
shift that we see
and the second is the detection of this
cosmic microwave background radiation
so it was first detected in the 1960s by
accident
purely by accident purely by chance and
those lucky guys who discovered it got
the nobel prize
for just stumbling into it then in the
late 1980s the first
proper survey of this radiation was done
a satellite called
cosmic background explorer was sent up
and it mapped
the the distribution of this radiation
it found that it is not completely
uniform there are anisotropies
and and other such patterns so so
it is an outcome of of primordial
quantum fluctuations in the very early
universe which which created regions of
less density and more density in over
densities etc
so we can see that pattern in the
distribution of cosmic microwave
background radiation today so in the
1980s you had
the cobe satellite then in the early
2000s you had a wmap
experiment a new satellite that was pent
up it gave us a better understanding
of cmbr and then recently about a decade
ago or so you had the planck satellite
planck experiment which gave us an even
better understanding
of this ancient radiation so that is
what
cosmic microwave background edition is
it's a very interesting uh
phenomenon it it essentially proves that
uh
that the big bang actually happened so
great question
okay this is by avinash if photons are
massless then why do they get affected
by gravity brilliant question
i mean these are the questions that our
school teachers should encourage us to
ask
so that's this is a great question we
know that photons are massless photons
are
packets of electromagnetic radiation
they are
localized disturbances in the universal
electromagnetic field which is a field
made up of electric and magnetic
magnetic fields so photons are localized
concentrations
of energy and as we know photons are
massless they contain energy they have a
wavelength
they have a frequency and this frequency
manifests itself in different colors
green
red maroon etc and that's what our brain
interprets as colors these different
frequencies so photons are massless
they travel at the speed of light and
yet they are affected by gravity isn't
that
a great paradox gravity is supposed to
affect massive objects if i have a
massive object i
let it go it drops to the ground that is
the force
of gravity but we find that even light
is affected by gravity even the
trajectory the the path
of light itself is bent by gravity how
on earth does it happen
so there are two ways of looking at it
let's look at it first from the
perspective of
general relativity which is
geometric dynamics it is the four
diamond it is the dynamics of
light and energy and mass or mass energy
and light
in the arena of four dimensional space
time
so wherever you have a mass it's going
to
warp space time it's going to curve
space time and anything that
travels in a straight line will have to
will be forced
by this curvature to travel in a curve
because the
the fabric of space-time itself has
curved it has warped
and that affects light too because light
also travels within space-time it cannot
travel outside of space-time
so since stay space-time is curved by a
mass
even the trajectory of a light beam
would get curved because of that so
that's the simplest way of looking at
why is light affected by gravity the
other way of looking at it
is to look at it from the perspective of
quantum mechanics now
the most famous equation in the world is
e equals
m c squared every mass has an equivalent
energy
and every energy has an equivalent mass
so light
has energy we all know that so light
because of its energy has an equivalent
mass
and that is what one could say what
causes
it to be affected by the force of
gravity so that is a different way of
looking of looking at it
so there are two ways of looking at it
they are they both give
give us different ideas but they both
essentially give us
a simple handle on why light despite
being massless photons despite being
massless
are very much affected by gravity so
that's a
good question very good question
this is by pravan acharya three
questions in one
good good i like the initiative question
one please talk about the constituents
of interstellar interstellar space
what is it made up of number two if
matter anti-matter annihilation produces
pure energy can it be a viable energy
source in the future
and three what's the difference between
quasars and pulsars okay what are the
constituents of interstellar space
at the macro level it's almost empty
it is almost it is a better vacuum than
anything we can produce on this earth
with our best technology so interstellar
space is mostly
empty it does have a very very
small density of molecules and atoms
and cosmic ray protons anti-protons
and atomic nuclei and all that but that
is a very very very
very minuscule density it also has some
dust particles and so on but it's mostly
empty
it's it's a better vacuum than anything
we can produce on earth
it also has stars and galaxies and
nebulae
and dark matter and dark energy and
at the at the quantum scale it the
the empty space is not empty it is
steaming
with virtual particles the
quantum fluctuations so what's a quantum
fluctuation
it is a temporary and random disturbance
or fluctuation in the energy of a point
in space
which is caused by the constraints
imposed by heisenberg's uncertainty
principle
so there are two ways of looking at the
uncertainty principle one is the
position
and momentum uh way of looking at it and
the other one is energy and time
so the so what happens is that it
in empty space just randomly
spontaneously you have this particle
anti-particle for
pairs being formed so a particle and
an anti-particle are formed and this
they quickly recombine
and disintegrate so even though this
violates the law of conservation of
energy you cannot have energy
from coming out of vacuum yet this
happens
but it happens so fast that it does not
violate
heisenberg's uncertainty principle and
that's why you have
this quantum this vast
array of quantum fluctuations in empty
space so this is
the energy of of vacuum it's called
vacuum energy
so that is what we have in interstellar
space in vacuum
at the quantum level now question number
two
if matter antimatter annihilation
produces pure energy
can it be a viable energy source in the
future theoretically
yes it could be a very good very
powerful and very efficient energy
source
it would have no pollution it would just
produce
pure energy the so yes
theoretically hypothetically it is a
very viable
energy source in the future a very small
amount of uh
matter anti-matter could give us a very
large amount of energy
a one rupee coin of mata and a one rupee
coin of antimatter if they annihilated
together
they could produce an explosion far
larger than the
the hiroshima atomic blast so that's the
kind of energy you have in such
such small in
such small amounts of matter and
anti-matter so it can be a very
useful and very uh very powerful source
of energy in the future
the problem is that we first of all
don't have any means of of producing
any significant quantities of antimatter
right
the little antimatter we produce
is mostly done in particle accelerators
and colliders
and we don't have any proper way of
storing it because it is so hard to
store the moment it interacts with
anything any ordinary matter it
essentially explodes
and gives out photons and gamma rays and
and x-rays
so that is the thing so we have to keep
it in a pure vacuum in a perfect vacuum
and a perfect vacuum doesn't even exist
in interstellar space
so it is very hard to bring such a
technology into fruition even though it
is
theoretically very much possible so it
it is something that's very challenging
and i don't see it happening in the next
100 years at least
but who knows let's see so it is
potentially a great
form of energy great source of energy
but as of now we are nowhere near
achieving uh even the first baby steps
in the direction
and question number three what is the
difference between quasars
and pulsars good question
let's start with quasars quasars are
active galactic nuclei that are
extremely
energetic so what's a galactic nucleus
it is
whatever is uh
located at the very center of a galaxy
so
galaxy is like a cyclone it has the same
shape as a cyclone or a typhoon
or a hurricane a spiral shape mostly
spiral galaxies are like that
so let's let's just take spiral galaxies
as an example
so at the center at the very core of a
spiral galaxy
you typically have a super massive black
hole our own milky way galaxy
has a supermassive black hole at the
center and we have recently
taken uh an image
of another supermassive black uh
supermassive black hole at the
the core of another galaxy so most
galaxies
have supermassive black holes at their
center and in some cases in some
galaxies
there is a very energetic accretion disk
around
this supermassive black hole such a
supermassive black hole is typically of
the order of
millions or even billions of solar
masses so that's how large it is
it has an enormous gravity and
in these active active galactic nuclei
you have an active process of accretion
so what's happening is that you have
stars and other material that is being
torn apart by the gravitational forces
so these
stars are shredded ripped and there's
this enormous disc
of super heated material around the
black hole and it's all trying to fall
into the
into the black hole in a vortex fashion
and it is this immense amount of
matter super heated matter that's
falling into this
monstrous black hole that that gives off
incredible
amounts of radiation so this is what's
known as
a quasar a quasar a quasi-stellar object
or a quasi-stellar radio source
there are two acronyms so the
luminosity of a quasar is incredible
a typical quasar gives off more light
and radiation in one second than a
thousand
milky way type galaxies can give off in
one second
so the milky way has approximately 400
billion stars
a thousand milky ways would have about
four
how many is it 400 trillion stars
and a single quasar gives off more light
and radiation than
400 trillion stars so you can imagine
the incredible power and luminous
luminosity
of this object of this astrophysical
object it's a
monstrous astrophysical object so that
is what a quasar
is it's an active galactic nucleus that
is incredibly luminous
and nothing can survive in its vicinity
i can guarantee that there's no life
that we can understand that we can
envisage in the in the vicinity of any
quasar
so that's what a quasar is what's a
pulsar
so a pulsar is a neutron star
that spins very fast and it gives
off uh electromagnetic radiation two
pulses or two jets of electromagnetic
radiation from its magnetic poles
so let me show you what a pulsar
typically looks like
here we have a typical pulsar this is a
neutron star that gives off
electromagnetic radiation from its
magnetic poles
it's it it has this kind of lighthouse
effect
so if you are in the
uh in the path of this light beam then
you will see a very regular
uh pulse of radiation from it so there
are certain pulsars that give off this
radiation
if you are in in its path they will give
off this
pulse of radiation every few seconds or
every 100 or so seconds and there are
these so-called millisecond pulsars too
which give off
which give off these pulses once every
millisecond
or so so these pulsars were first
discovered
uh because of radio astronomy etc
and what was found is that we had we had
these big
beeps coming out of interstellar space
this beeping sounds
in the radio frequencies and nobody
could explain what these what these were
people thought that these may be
extraterrestrials who are trying to
communicate with us
but later we found out that these were
actually neutron stars that give off
these
these two uh jets of of radiation
and because the spin is so fast
because of conservation of angular
momentum that's why we have these very
rapid pulses and extremely precisely
timed pulses
of radio waves and other other forms of
radiation that come out of there
so that is what a pulsar is it's a
neutron star that gives off these two
jets
these two beams of light and radio waves
okay good questions so that's the
difference between quasars and pulsars
very different objects very different
astrophysical objects okay next question
huh okay similar question what are
pulsars
and what's the difference between
neutron stars and magnetars
so i just explained what a pulsar is
now what is the difference between
neutron stars and magnetar so let's
start with
neutron stars a neutron star
is a core collapse remnant
of a is the is the is the remnant of a
supernova of a core collapse
supernova so typically you have
a neutron star is formed after the
supernova
of a supermassive star
a star that is typically between 10 and
25 solar masses
a super giant star right so when a super
giant star
reaches the end of its life it it
essentially stops
burning fuel uh in a fusion reaction
so it typically happens when you have
the formation of iron
in its core that's when the fusion react
reaction stops because iron is not
nuclear fuel
it is nuclear ash so the moment iron is
formed from fusion
so fusion happens by the fusion of of uh
to
nuclei hydrogen nuclei from
fuse together to form helium and then
you have heavier elements that
are formed you have uh you have oxygen
you have carbon you have neon and then
it reaches the stage of iron
and once all the neon is used up and you
you reach iron
that's when a star is essentially dead
it has just a few seconds of life left
and that's when stellar collapse happens
and after the collapse of when when the
star starts imploding
the core of the star is really
compressed very very strongly
and protons and electrons combine
and form neutrons and so the core
becomes just
formed of neutrons only only neutrons
nothing else
and then the supernova happens with
whatever material is left in the star
and at the end of the supernova what is
left behind at the center
of where the star once was is a neutron
star
so a neutron star is is is typically
a small star between 1.4 solar masses
and and around two solar masses anything
larger than three solar masses it will
become a black hole
so that is what a neutron star is it is
the most compact
and dense object in the known universe
apart from black holes
so that is what a neutron star is it's
formed off it is composed almost
entirely of neutrons
now what's a pulsar like i said a pulsar
is a neutron star
which spins very rapidly and gives off
two beams of
electromagnetic radiation typically
radio waves in two opposite directions
and it pulses extremely
in a very periodic manner what is a
magnetar
a magnetar is again another neutron star
which is an extremely
powerful magnetic field so the magnetic
field
of a magnetar is typically hundreds of
millions of times stronger than the most
powerful
man-made magnet available on earth it's
an extremely
powerful magnetic field it is trillions
of times more powerful than the magnetic
field of the earth itself
now it is the evolution and decay
of this magnetic field in a magnetar
that gives off
extremely powerful bursts of radiation
typically in the x-ray and gamma-ray
spectra
and this is what's known as a soft gamma
repeater so this
is the astrophysical source of the
phenomenon known as the
soft gamma repeater phenomenon right so
that's what a magnetar is it is a
neutron star with a very very
incredibly powerful magnetic field these
are
incredibly interesting fascinating and
exotic objects
and this is the kind of
phenomena that the laws of nature throw
up
so great question
okay this is by priyam sodia
we know for a fact that the universe is
expanding because galaxies are moving
away from us then why
is andromeda moving towards our galaxy
is it because the milky way and
andromeda are moving towards the great
attractor very good question
so we know that the universe is
expanding i went into that in some
detail
and yet uh you are right your your
observation is correct
the milky way and our closest
neighboring galaxy
andromeda we are these two galaxies are
moving
towards each other and about in about
four and a half or five billion years
from today
the two galaxies will collide there will
be a collision or a merger of sorts
and they will eventually combine
together to form a massive a more
massive galaxy
which people call milko media or
something like that
so that's about 5 billion plus years in
the future
so if the universe is expanding if the
expansion
is accelerating then why is the milky
way and andromeda
why are these two galaxies moving
towards each other
and is it because of the great attractor
so what is the great attractor
it is a gravitational anomaly that is
invisible to us
it is it is uh present in the
local super cluster the uh the what is
it called it's called the laniakea super
cluster
which is about a it's a cluster of about
10 000 or so galaxies
the milky way and andromeda are part of
that
so there is at the center of mass of
this supercluster
gravitational anomaly which we are not
able to see from here
because it lies in the in the in the
beyond our
the plane of our galaxy itself so we
cannot observe it directly from here
from from the earth so it is a
gravitational anomaly it is a very very
massive
uh object of some kind uh
and it is about 200 or 250 million light
years away
from where we are so is it
what is causing andromeda and us to come
towards
each other no it is not andromeda and
the milky way are just two and a half
million light years away from each other
so they are much closer to each other
than the
laniakea super cluster the the great
attractor at the center of the
laniakea supercluster so the reason
these two galaxies are coming towards
each other is because the expansion of
the universe
happens at the largest scales the
density of dark energy
is less than is on the of the order of
10 raised to minus 30 grams per cubic
centimeter
which is extremely incredibly dilute so
it does not
affect uh space-time at local scales
at the scales of galaxy clusters and the
like
it only affects space-time at the very
very very larger scales
the scales of superstructures and dark
microfilaments
and the very largest structures in the
universe
so that's why the local gravity of these
two galaxies
is able to overpower the very weak
effect very weak local effect of dark
energy and that's why they are moving
towards each other
it has nothing to do with the
so-called great attractor which we
really don't understand what it is it's
probably something we are unable to see
because our galaxy the plane of our
galaxy gets in the way
so to answer your question it's because
in the local
in the local scale gravity overpowers
dark energy that is the answer in brief
okay this is by rahul this is by rahul
ranganath
do you think the arrow of time can be
reversed there have been reports that
entropy can be reversed on a microscopic
scale
which can in which in turn can reverse
the flow of time
if it can be done on a micro scale isn't
it a matter of time until we get a major
breakthrough on the macroscopic scale
wouldn't that violate the second law of
thermodynamics okay good question
entropy is a measure of the statistical
disorder
of any system right so
we can definitely reverse entropy
on a small scale for example i have
um you you can have a crystal or you can
have a bottle
so this is a very orderly structure it
is a man-made
object there is no disorder in this
except for the water if i empty the
water then it's a very ordered
system of course it will have oxygen
molecules air molecules and all
but you get my point so we can create
local
uh regions of low gravity our brain is
the lowest
of low entropy sorry our human brain is
the
most complex and most powerful
biological computer or any kind of
computer known
in known to us in the known universe so
that is a region of
incredibly low entropy because it is so
well ordered
so you can have localized regions of
very low entropy
and yet to produce a local
small region of low entropy you have to
it is inevitable that to produce low
entropy local
locally you will end up increasing the
entropy of the overall system that
you're in
so we we are part of the environment
that we are in we have atmosphere
so to produce something like a plastic
bottle you have to do some melting
of of plastic and some other mechanical
processes which produce heat
and heat is uh which it increases the
the entropy of the atmosphere so no
matter what process you do
you may be able to decrease the entropy
at a local level
but you will overall in the system end
up
increasing its entropy or at the very
best keeping the entropy the same
so so that's the answer to your question
it can be reversed or
on a on a small scale but it cannot
reverse the
okay about the flow of time so it's a
hypothesis that
time is related to entropy that try
maybe an
emergent phenomenon it's a hypothesis we
don't know if it's true or not
we don't have any valid or coherent or
well accepted uh theory of time
we don't know if it is a fundamental
property of the universe whether it's an
emergent phenomenon
whether you have you may whether you can
have
molecules or atoms of time we it appears
that time
doesn't even exist to some extent on at
the quantum scale
past present and future seem to be i
mean meaningless concepts at the quantum
level too
so we don't really know what time is
it is a great mystery it is one of the
big mysteries of physics
and is it connected to entropy is it
connected to thermodynamics
there are certain speculations and
hypotheses but there is no
actual uh uh
falsifiable theory of this so we don't
know i don't know if it is
as of now without sufficient data i
cannot say
yes or no either way maybe right
so i don't know if the error of time can
be reversed it is possible that
you may have an entire universe in which
time flows backwards so there is this uh
problem called the baryon asymmetry
problem we only see matter in the
universe we don't see any anti-matter
but the universe according to all the
known theories should have produced
equal amounts of matter and anti-matter
so where is all the anti-matter so there
is a theory that there is that the big
bang produced two universes
a posit a universe and an anti-universe
the universe that we are in is full of
regular matter
and the our counterpart counterpart
anti-universe has
anti-matter and maybe the time the era
of time for
flows in the opposite direction in that
universe so that again is a hypothesis
it's just a theory we have no way of uh
either proving it or falsifying it so as
of now
with the understanding of the laws of
nature that we have
this question about the era of time
cannot be answered
at this stage we are still taking baby
steps in our understanding of the
phenomenon of time
but this is a great question
okay so rajit kosh asks is space really
empty
if yes then how do rockets propel
themselves forward
so like i said earlier space is mostly
empty but at the quantum scale it's full
of quantum fluctuations
in the various fields that are part of
space
of space at the quantum level that is
something that comes out of the theory
that is called quantum field theory
but for the sake of for macroscopic
objects like rockets it doesn't matter
at all
these quantum fluctuations are
immaterial so
if space is empty like it it mostly is
then how do rockets propel themselves
forward
it's a good question so if i want to
if i were to push on a wall then it will
push me back right
if i were to impart a force a strong
force
on the floor then i'll be able to jump
upwards
so you need to push against something in
order to get a reaction
and that's what we experience in our
ordinary day-to-day life
now let's assume that you are standing
on a skateboard
okay you're standing on a skateboard
which is a very movable
platform and you're holding a machine
gun
and you let it go bang bang bang bang
bang so each time you fire a bullet
that bullet flow bullet flies off at a
few kilometers per second
and because of the law because of
newton's
third law of motion action reaction you
will
you will experience a massive recoil in
the rifle
and because you're on a skateboard you
will be physically pushed back and the
skateboard will roll in the opposite
direction
so even though you're not pushing
against the wall or anything at all
you have this action and reaction
phenomenon
this happens even if you're standing on
ice ice is a very slippery
slippery surface there is very less
friction so again if you fire a rifle
standing on ice you're gonna go shooting
in the opposite direction
so this happens even in space if you
were able to fire a rifle in space
the bullet would go in one direction and
you would go back in the other direction
and this is basically uh the
conservation of linear momentum it's
it's
that is the principle that's behind this
and that is how rockets work
so a rocket may be in the vacuum of
space it ejects
a very energetic and powerful stream of
gases from its nozzle
and this ejection of gases makes the
rocket move
in the other direction and that's how
rocket propulsion
works in the vacuum of space i hope
that is able to answer your question
one more question before we end
priyam asks that it was hypothesized
gravity should be excluded from the
set of fundamental forces as gravity is
curvature of space time not a force
instead a new force called quintessence
should replace gravity as a fundamental
force i support this hypothesis because
gravity works
on larger scales and the other three
forces work on the quantum level
and the graviton the boson for gravity
doesn't exist
the other forces have their own bosons
what's my take on this okay
so we don't know how gravity works at
this
quantum level we it is incorrect to say
that it doesn't work at the quantum
level
all we know is that we don't have a
coherent
and valid theory of gravity at the
quantum level
we are unable to quantize space-time
at the macro the microscopic level
quantum field theory
the equations of quantum field theory
the the laws of quantum field theory
don't work
in curved space time they break down so
there is a gap in our understanding
it is not a gap in in the laws of nature
so we don't know about gravity is there
is there actually some quantum theory of
gravity
does grav gravity actually work on the
quantum scale or is it something that
emerges only in
in geometry in the geometry of space
time as of now we don't know
does the graviton exist we haven't thus
far found any evidence of the
hypothetical graviton
it doesn't mean it doesn't exist it
means we haven't found it
it is a valid theory and it is a
falsifiable theory
so we are working towards either
validating it or falsifying it
now about so should gravity be excluded
from the set of forces
as of now no because it has not been
proven to not be a force
it could still be a force at the quantum
scale
it is a matter of being able to prove or
disprove
this particular thing and basically we
are trying to formulate
a coherent theory of quantum gravity now
what is quintessence
quintessence is a quintessence is a
scalar field
it is a it is a dynamic field that is it
is not uh
it was not introduced to replace gravity
it was introduced
as a means of trying to uh explain what
dark energy is
so like i said quintessence is a
hypothetical scalar field that permeates
space time it's dynamic it's it's time
dependent
so it is it can be either attractive
or repulsive depending on various
circumstances and conditions
so it is it is hypothesized or theorized
that quintessence was attractive in the
first three or four billion years
of the universe lifetime and after that
it became a repulsive force
and as we know dark energy was less in
the past it is more today it is
increasing
so quintessence is a hypothetical or
theoretical attempt to explain
dark energy it cannot replace gravity
itself
yeah quintessence is by
can be thought of as a possible
hypothetical
fifth force of nature but as of now this
theory is uh
is essentially in its infancy and there
is no way of either proving it or or
or falsifying it as we speak today
so there are many such theories that are
attempting to
uh resolve these massive problems that
we are facing
and these enormous unanswered questions
that we have as of now
but i would not as of now try to want to
exclude gravity
as a fundamental force so the i hope
that answers your question
priyam let me take a couple of questions
from the live chat before we end this
like i said i'm gonna do more episodes
of astrophysics you have asked me
so many brilliant questions i'm gonna
have to do more episodes
so i'm gonna take a couple of more
questions quickly and then we will end
for today
but we will do this again
okay let me see a couple of good
questions if i can find some
this is by one second
this is by s do the laws of matter hold
inside a black hole if yes where do they
go once it enters so we don't know
what's inside a black hole we have
absolutely
no idea of what exists beyond the
event horizon of a black hole uh the
theory of general relativity tells you
that
space time curves toward infinite extent
at the center of a black hole and the
density of matter also becomes infinity
at the center of a black hole so this is
called the so-called
singularity so this most likely
indicates that
the laws of general relativity the
theory of general relativity does not
hold
at the quantum scale that's what it most
likely indicates
it the the so-called singularity most
likely doesn't really exist
but as of now with the laws of physics
that we have
we don't know what's inside a black hole
we know that the black hole
has mass we know that the black hole is
angular momentum
and we know that a black hole has charge
it has a magnetic field apart from that
we don't really know
anything else about what's inside the
black hole what happens once matter goes
inside
does it get converted into energy does
it get compressed to an infinitely
massive infinitely dense point
as of now we don't know and that's what
makes black hole physics so exciting
that very there is so little we know so
there is so much to discover
okay let's see
one more question
let me find let me find some good
question
quantum low gravity vapes dimensions
can i explain singularity i did that
okay what's the probable shape of the
universe in one sentence in one word
it's probably a sphere the observable
universe is spherical the
the universe beyond our cosmic horizon
we don't know
okay amaresh asks what is ligo and its
application in real life
can we cross the solar system and enter
into another hypothetically we could
cross the solar system and
reach the nearest star system which is
proxima centauri
uh it has an exoplanet called proxima
centauri b
it is possible we may be able to send
probes within the next 30 40 50 years
definitely
so it's possible but these are robotic
probes human beings still cannot
do that in one human lifetime what is
ligo it's a gravitational wave detector
it detects gravitational waves based on
interference patterns produced by laser
laser beams in very short so
it is essentially a large michelson
interferometer kind of
apparatus that uses the interference of
laser pulses and the effect it has on
mirrors etc
to detect waves and distortions in space
time goes by
gravitational waves that's what it is
i think that's all for today thank you
guys for
your brilliant questions
i'm going to end for now we will have a
different session later
i will do more sessions on astrophysics
quantum physics and all of this i know
you guys are really interested in this
so we'll do many more of this but for
today
it's uh this session ends now and i will
see you
tomorrow thank you for participating
have a great day have a great night
bye